[SPEAKER_00]: So, I've got a few questions that I would like... Well, I'll just...
[SPEAKER_00]: The one main question I have is specifically about something that I've been experiencing now, coming to quite a different place, mainly South Africa, and meeting, you know, ordinary, I would say, people who
[SPEAKER_00]: Just live ordinary lives with lots of pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, the way they relax is through maybe drinking and just having fun, you know, various types of fun.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, good people and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the main thing I see is that a lot of people, you know, people suffer from so much loss and deep loss
[SPEAKER_00]: And despite the amount of friends, the amount of fun, the amount of alcohol used to find some peace and happiness, none of that helps with the deepest of loss, you know, the loss of a husband, the loss of money.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, now, yeah, that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The most painful loss that I saw recently, was someone has recently lost their child, their son.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, I mean, these, the parents are in such tremendous turmoil, such tremendous depression and pain, that, you know, it really shows you that
[SPEAKER_00]: That sutta that says, you know, that one who is dear, and the Buddha, you know, that that's the man who loses his son, and the Buddha says, yeah, that's that's the way it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: With one, when you lose one who is dear, you suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I'm wondering, like, what advice, you know, they asked me how to how to help, what can I do to overcome this suffering of loss?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, see, the problem with that is,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's kind of too late to be able to just deal with that suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, most of the life has already been lived unwholesomely or unwisely.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now, this loss, the weight of this loss now, is the result of everything else from before.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if the lives were lived more wisely, the weight of the loss
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter how great it is, it won't be as heavy.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you know, when people usually ask at that stage, what do I do with this pain?
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, just, eh... can you get rid of it for me?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the first, pretty much the only thing they can do to begin, at least, facing the right direction of development is to... well, you have to stop resisting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to accept the facts.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to accept that, you know, your child is gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just... And if you accept it, then certain other things might become apparent through that, such as, well, yeah, okay, it came, it went, as that sutta says.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't know where it came from and you don't know where it's going.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is there to grieve for?
[SPEAKER_01]: But fundamentally, you need to stop resisting the pain of it internally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the habit of the entire life is to resist this discomfort and indulge the comfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, when you're struck by a, you know, unthinkable discomfort of losing your child, you're resisting it on a... on these very, very, very high levels of resistance.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it hurts so much.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because you lost your child, it's just because it is unacceptable to you, that reality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what you can do for them is just try to help them accept it, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not get rid of it, just accept it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they might not want to do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: They might just want to get rid of the pain and then not listen to whatever else you have to say.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's as far as your help can go, really, for somebody who is on that level.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Actually, I did, in fact, I mentioned that, that you have to accept that pain and be at peace with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, you know, obviously, try to understand it, that feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: But...
[SPEAKER_00]: And they also mentioned to me that they were accepting it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, every day they face it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's true, they do.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, at the same time, they are facing it with... while being intoxicated.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, although you are intoxicated and facing the pain, you know, you're talking about the loss, you're talking over and over and about it, crying about it, you are intoxicated at the same time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, are you really facing it?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the weight of the loss, the weight of the pain, is not determined by what you lost, it's determined by the state of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the state of your mind has been cultivated and it's determined in return by your behavior.
[SPEAKER_01]: By whether you've been scratching it, whether you have been refraining from it, whether you've been developing wisdom, whether you haven't been developing wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, exactly, the reason why they cannot not resist it so much, is because those are the mental habits they've been cultivating their entire life.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, lack of restraint, lack of composure, lack of patience, all these things that are normal, normal, normal for people.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, then you realize, because of those things, you are liable to the greater weight of pain, than you would have experienced otherwise, if you actually developed, you know, wisdom, patience, sense restraint and virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, again, like, you know, people, at best of times, don't want to hear about virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let alone, when they're gripped by that pain and resistance, and you tell them about sensory strain, they're not going to see a connection between the two at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's not really much you can do at that stage, unless, you know, they somehow manage to calm down, and then, sort of, click in their mind that
[SPEAKER_01]: Hey, how about... is there anything that I can do about this now, you know?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, from a more rational point of view, as opposed to just... just, you know, get rid of this pain while I'm half drunk, basically, because I don't know how to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, maybe, you know, they might be able to listen and hear it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That, you know, the mind can be developed regardless of what you've been through.
[SPEAKER_01]: But until then, there's not really much you can do.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what you can do though, is those who haven't lost, and those who might hear, use that as an example for them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, don't wait until it's too late.
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you know, yeah, essentially, it's learning to deal with pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, not crave against it, but also... but to learn how to deal with these little pains in your life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's what the training is, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't... it's learning to deal with pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like learning a technique or a psychological method.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's really developing your mind, so when the pain touches it, the mind doesn't move, because it doesn't feel it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if the mind is not developed, the slightest pain will make it move.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's almost like a training.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, like when you train a response, like drilling in order for a right response in certain environment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, this is the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're drilling non-resistance to pain and you do that on the level of these small pains and discomforts.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the training.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that then, when the pains of bigger kind come, the principle of non-resistance is there to some extent, to some degree.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's the whole point then.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you will have that space mentally, because you're not irrationally resisting that pain, you will have that space to see more, without needing... without being overwhelmed by the pressure to manage that pain, deal with it and get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you will not have that space if you haven't been training your mind in regard to the pain, however subtle or however big.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to wait for the big pains in order to start the training.
[SPEAKER_01]: Quite the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, keeping the precepts already is a form of pain for somebody who is not trained in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sensory strength, moderation in eating, being watchful of your speech and actions, it's all a form of, you know, confinement and discomfort because you were spilling outside of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But see, that's a good pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a pain that will make your mind develop and not move, so that then, when pains of other kind come, pain of loss, whether loss of your life and health and wealth and so on, or loss of your family, things that are dear to you,
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, there is some basis of training of non-resistance towards discomfort, but you can't just wish non-resistance.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can either train it or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you trained it, mind will not resist it, because it's been conditioned to not resist.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you haven't, it will resist, even if you wish for it to not resist.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the... you can really see the benefits of that kind of training, that, you know, training in sīla.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's the wisdom, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, the problem with... there is no direct, seemingly, the direct connection between sīla and that inability to suffer as much.
[SPEAKER_01]: That connection is not visible.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where the wisdom comes in.
[SPEAKER_01]: The people that have this sermon and wisdom can sort of see that connection, however faint it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: But people who can't see it, then it will be even harder for them to commit to the effort of sīla and sense restraint and gradual training.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why either, you know, you arrive at that effort through faith or through discernment.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if people have neither, it's virtually impossible to train, rightly, because why would you do it when there is seemingly absolutely no good reason for it?
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to understand that reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either understand it, or just have faith in it, because, you know, you have other... you have faith in other things that the Buddha said, so he also said this, so you just have faith in it, and on account of that faith, you do the work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just, I have faith in it, and I don't do the work.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point is to do the work, whether it's done on account of faith, or on account of understanding and discernment, doesn't matter, as long as you do the work.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how a person deals with the loss,
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't wait until you lose something in order to deal with the loss.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's already the beginning of wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: You already recognize that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, my children are all fine, but they could not be so.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things could change.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, is that thought scaring me?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I ignoring it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, if, say, something like that happens, will my mind remain unmoved?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, to what extent it would move?
[SPEAKER_01]: And you recognize, oh, that is a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I could, whatever, disown my children or something or never have children.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but still, you are liable to your mind moving on account of loss, losing things that are dear to you, children or something else, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what life is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you recognize, okay, so it's about training the mind to not move and not lose perspective and not be overwhelmed by pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not resist it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And how do you train that?
[SPEAKER_01]: By that point, see, if you already see that as a worthy goal, to train, like, to train towards being able to deal with the loss before you lose things, then all the gradual training and things the Buddha talks about will already make much more sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you need to be willing to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly, yeah, that's like to get a better, clearer perspective on the nature of your situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: What you're liable to, where you're heading, where your actions and ambitions taking you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Are they sort of aligned with the nature of things you're liable to?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or are they based on ignoring the nature of things you're liable to?
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you pretending everything will always be fine forever?
[SPEAKER_01]: And act accordingly?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or are you actually keeping that in mind that, you know, your life will not last forever, your health will not last forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things inevitably are subject to change and it will have to happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there's a kind of mantra that I hear often now.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's like, sure, I will get old, I will get sick, maybe I will die, you know, I might lose this and I might lose that, but I'll deal with that.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll deal with that when it comes, when it happens.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't have to deal with that now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just like that idea, I'll deal with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, ask yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just in the limited experience that you have in your life, was it better when you dealt with things when you were prepared or when you were unprepared?
[SPEAKER_01]: Which has a better chance of dealing with it properly?
[SPEAKER_01]: When you were ready, when you didn't lose, when you didn't slip, when you didn't lose the sight of the problem, or when you were completely pretending, oh, I won't worry about it, and then when it comes, I'll deal with it?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, is it better when you're trained to deal with it, or is it better when you're untrained and then just deal with it on the fly?
[SPEAKER_01]: You already know the answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, better train for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, you'll deal with it when it comes, but it's better to be able to know how to deal with it when it comes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not wait for it to come and then hope you're gonna kind of, you know, manage to float on top of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, when you look at... because you actually are always training something, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are always choosing and acting in some direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either it's going to be direction of development that... well, the direction that contributes towards the development of the mind and removal of resistance towards pain, or it's going to be a direction that basically takes away from that development and increases the resistance towards pain by habit, by response.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's... and, you know, if I can just talk about, like, the habit of, say, drinking, you know, alcohol, and you can see, you know, not everybody's an alcoholic and so on, but it's this... you go to work and there's... and the pre... you know, every day, Monday to Friday or whatever, and the pressure builds up,
[SPEAKER_00]: The pressure of your duties and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the only way you can relax is through, you know, through substances, through either distraction, through alcohol, for example, particularly alcohol, as I'm talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that relaxes you, you know, that sort of releases some of that pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So now what you are training yourself to do is, now I feel a bit of pressure, and I go to alcohol, and you can be relieved and feel relaxed.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what you are training now is that every time you feel pressure, your way of relief is through alcohol, for example, you know, just to put it that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So now, and are you liable to have more pressure in your life through other things such as loss, loss of your limbs, loss of your friends and family and so on?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, when that pressure hits you, what are you going to do?
[SPEAKER_00]: You're going to do the thing that you've been doing all this time to relieve yourself of pressure, which is alcohol.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, when you do that, so you have that, you have your drink, and the pressure is not relieved, because it's so great.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, what do you have to do?
[SPEAKER_00]: You just have to drink more, but the pressure is still not relieved, so you have to drink more and continue doing that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's that danger of having that one drink to relieve that one small pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, the danger is not in the alcohol, the danger is in the attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: The danger is in the attitude of, I will use these external means to to pacify myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, you still use, basically, forms of sensuality to find peace.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, you have a view that that is peaceful.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, eh... and that's the risk, that's the peril.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's your attitude of giving in to the weakness for the sake of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's making you not able to handle that... Well, exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're giving in to that weakness, however ridiculous it is, however small it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: The whole principle of training is to not seek peace and escape externally, but be able to not move by... be moved by it internally.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if you just, you know, I drink only on social occasions, I don't get drunk, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're giving in to that pressure for the sake of comfort, for the sake of not standing out, whatever else it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are giving in to the principle that is against the training of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you are moving.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are moved by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when something bigger happens, when some greater pressure tries to move you, again, you will leak through that opening.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, and then it's going to become even bigger opening, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's... that's what I said in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what the Buddha meant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, untrained asuta or puthujjana basically has no other... does not know any other escape from arisen painful feeling, any other escape than sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whether it's alcohol, distractions, whatever else, it's all based on the pleasures of your senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to be informed, suttava, enough to recognize that that's a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Although it feels the most natural thing to do, it's actually a problem and I should start refraining from going in that direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Although I don't quite see directly why or how, I can make some sense that this is aggravating my problem and perhaps sensory strength is the way to go.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you start the sensory strength, and then you get to learn more, and then you get to start seeing benefits for yourself directly on account of that training.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not before you actually start doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because sometimes people want to have it all reasoned out and proven that it will work before they even start doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you cannot understand how it feels to be completely dry while you never refuse... while you... while you refuse to leave the water, while you're constantly immersed in water.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to actually physically remove yourself from it, and then you won't need any intellectual convincing and so on, because, oh, you are drying up properly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's that first step of faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, either based on faith or some degree of reasoning, but it needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's sīla comes first and it never leaves.
[SPEAKER_01]: It stays as a framework through which you then grow and develop further.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, it's very important to realize the nature of your situation and start doing it before the pressure accumulates of the kind that you now just cannot even cope with by the means you're used to.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, sometimes people can turn it around, you know, but generally, yeah, you've been scratching your itch so hard, there is nothing else you know now in the world except that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're pretty much like an animal, just responding to a stimuli.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's... that's very tough.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, again, it's just... it's... it's the accumulated condition.
[SPEAKER_01]: It didn't happen overnight.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why, oh, now, in order to overcome it, it's gonna take a while for you to... to undo everything that you basically acquired.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through the wrong actions and lack of wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I also thought, you know, how valuable it is to actually meet someone who has overcome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's like a divine messenger.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you could see how much generally darkness there is in the world, in people's minds.
[SPEAKER_01]: By that, I mean, like, they don't really have a concept of what's right, what's good, what's beneficial, what it isn't, what brings mind to develop, what brings mind to kind of decrease.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, meeting somebody who can actually point that out, yeah, yeah, it's quite rare and... Because even, you know, you can... it's difficult to reason these things, but then when you actually see the physical presence of someone who has done it or whatever, that is... that's more like, oh, yeah, oh, it's... oh, it's possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it's possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's the samana-sañña, the whole... the proper, like the perception of...
[SPEAKER_01]: of somebody who's actually... oh, look, somebody did this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just us seeing the... being inspired by the robe or the Buddha statues.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean... oh, no, look, possibility of freedom has been actualized by somebody.
Actual, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, made actual.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, maybe I can do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe I can at least make some effort towards it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's rare to see people who have actualized it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's also rare to recognize the value of it, even if you see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I think most people would recognize it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, it would affect most people that see someone complete.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, they would, yeah, they would not be able to, to completely not notice it.